There's a reason you know this book.
Even if you've never heard of the TV show,
...you for sure seen some of these images in here.
They're the example illustrations for a
lot of Wikipedia pages on body parts.
They're just-
They're gorgeous illustrations, right.
But here's the deal:
I'm...
...always wary whenever something within education
...takes on, like, a legendary status.
And...
...this thing's been in existence since,
...I mean, over a hundred and fifty years.
So, I had some questions.
At the end of the day,
...Gray's Anatomy is still just a book,
...so what makes it so special?
How did Gray's Anatomy become a thing?
The story starts in:
This is the institution where
...the namesake behind the book,
...began his career and met the book's illustrator.
That college featured one of the best dissection rooms
...at one of the best hospitals in London.
And as you'll see later,
...Gray would need to do a lot of dissections.
And somewhere around that time,
...Gray met a younger student at St. George
...named Henry Vandyke* Carter.
He was trained as an apothecary
...but was going to school to become a physician.
And way before he started working with Gray,
...he got experience
...creating medical illustrations for
the college and local museums.
This is what made Carter so special.
He was a doctor
...so he could dissect a body or look
through the microscope first-hand,
...but he was also an artist
...who could draw accurate pictures of that body part
...or whatever he saw on the slide.
And in 1853,
...Gray happened to be in the market for some drawings.
He had just finished a massive essay about the spleen,
...and got contacted by a local
father-son publishing company to:
So naturally,
...Gray went to Carter for the art work.
And surprise!
A 300-page book about the spleen
...did not sell very well.
So the publishers actually took
a financial hit on that book,
...but it did start a working relationship with
both Gray and Carter for future projects.
In a few years later,
...they came back to them with the idea
...for a little textbook.
The plan was simple:
Make a high-quality General Anatomy textbook
...that would actually sell.
This book would be a manual for surgeons
...so it had to be big enough to read at a distance
...but small enough to fit in the operating room.
At the time,
...most textbooks used tiny pictures
with lots of wordy footnotes.
So to take advantage of the page real estate,
...the illustrator would need to draw enormous pictures
...and use captions that fit around them.
To get an even bigger picture,
...they could write the names of structures on the image
...to save space and eliminate extra captions.
The publishers also knew the book
...had to be more affordable than its competition,
...so details like binding would
have to be kept to a minimum.
Nothing fancy.
...that students would want to buy.
Gray was a good anatomy teacher,
...so he was the natural choice as the writer.
And since they'd worked together before,
...Carter was exactly the illustrator for the job.
The plan was to do about 300 illustrations,
...which meant they were gonna
need some models to draw.
And while they already had a few
specimens at the university,
...it was pretty clear from the beginning
...they were gonna need to do some fresh dissections,
...which is kind of a big deal.
To put things in perspective,
...only 90 years earlier,
...a man named William Hunter
...wanted to write a book about the human uterus.
He got:
...over the course of:
To hit their deadline,
...Gray and Carter would have to make
their drawings and dissections in:
They would be able to recycle
some content from the college,
...but they still needed fresh bodies,
...which begs the question:
Just how do you get a dead body?
In the 1700s,
...England passed legislation that said:
...after they'd been hanged.
But thanks to all these medical schools popping up,
...the number of corpses needed
...outgrew the number of corpses available.
This gave rise to:
Men who dug up freshly buried bodies
...and sold them back to medical schools.
And as you can imagine,
...people weren't exactly down
with this rise of grave-robbing,
...so they pressured the government to change the law.
And in:
...Parliament passed:
As long as a patient's family
didn't object within 48 hours,
...universities could take a corpse
directly from hospital bed
...to dissection table.
It gave students a fresh body to work on
...and eliminated the market for grave robbers.
If the phrasing of that law sounds a little suspect,
...it's because it was.
Like, how long did families have to claim their bodies?
Does the 48-hour timer start after death
...or after the family had been notified?
What about people with no family?
Like, what if you were found dead in the workhouse,
...or homeless on the street in the middle of winter?
This new legislation put bodies on dissection tables,
...but it did so at the expense
of the poor and disadvantaged.
And Gray was able to use this broken pipeline
...to get plenty of bodies.
As a physician,
...he made decisions about where bodies
went after pronouncing them dead.
And while I'm not making any judgments,
...some historians suspect that he
used more bodies for dissection
...than his documentation shows.
So that became the routine:
From February of 1856
...to July of 1857,
...a body would come into the dissection room,
...these two guys would do their cuts,
...they'd look under the microscope,
...then Gray would write some words
...and Carter would do some drawings.
Working together,
...they were able to check each other's work
...and put words to pictures and vice versa.
And Carter didn't just draw with pen on paper.
He drew in a way that translated to:
...the printing technology of
choice for books at that time.
That might seem like an unimportant technique,
...but it helped eliminate middlemen,
...which ultimately kept the cost of the book down.
After the manuscript was done,
...now the publishers had to sell it.
They knew it would do better than the spleen book,
...but once it actually hit the shelves
...it blew away their expectations.
To understand why,
...put yourself in the shoes of
a medical student back then.
You'd probably buy one high-quality
textbook at the beginning of med school
....that would last you for years.
So if you're in a bookstore and you see:
...with its massive illustrations,
...next to the wordy pages of its competition like:
...it was no question.
Gray's Anatomy was such a hit
...because it was the best book available at the time.
Now, unfortunately,
...Gray had one thing he wanted to edit
after the manuscript was submitted:
The title page.
Just change Carter's title
...and make that text just a little bit smaller.
Oh, and only Gray's name on the spine.
Now, don't feel too bad.
Gray got smallpox and died, like, two years later
...while working on the second edition of the book.
And the financial success of the book never stopped.
The publishers sold out of the first edition
...and got to work on a second,
...and another and another.
And the sales kept going,
...where today is on its 41st edition
...under Elsevier.
So why was Grey's Anatomy so successful?
It's because it was a high-quality book.
Why is it still successful?
Well, it never stopped making money.
Now, that surface-level answer seems tempting to keep:
"Gray's Anatomy was a success"
"...because two talented men
put out a high-quality product."
But that's not the conclusion I want to draw.
This book wouldn't have been
possible to write and illustrate
...if it weren't for bodies to dissect.
And thanks to the Anatomy Act
...and the socioeconomic situation at the time,
...those bodies tended to belong to the
poorest and most vulnerable of society.
It didn't matter that the family wanted a proper burial
...if we needed an intestine dissection for next week.
As Ruth Richardson puts it in her book:
So, yes.
Talented people put high-quality
work into Gray's Anatomy,
...but that work was only possible
...because disadvantaged people
gave their lives to make that happen.
Cool, so now that everyone's thoroughly depressed,
...what do we do with this information?
If you're like me, you love anatomy.
You love the human body
...but it's easy to fall into this very reductionist mindset:
"Bodies are either healthy,"
"...or bodies have disease."
But every body that you come across,
...whether it is a living patient, a cadaver,
...or a name in a case study,
...is attached to a human life
...and has a story.
Have fun,
...be good.
Thanks for watching.
Thank you for watching this video to the very end.
I'm really excited that more and more
people are down to hear these stories,
...and I really want to keep that going,
...so I have a favor to ask.
If you get any enjoyment out of this video,
...or if I helped you learn something,
...would you mind sharing your favorite video
...with just one friend?
I mean, clearly you have exquisite taste
...you watch this channel,
...and I feel like we just need to, you know,
...share the wealth a little bit.
Yeah. Alternatively, if you want to, like, you know,
...share the social media thing,
...all of my handles are:
If you want to hear more medical history,
...you can go ahead and click on that playlist right there.
And of course,
...subscribe.
Patreon is right here.
Thanks again for watching. I-
This is a lot of fun.
Thank you, everybody.
[snap]